Mithlesh Upadhyay

Data Scientist | Gen Al/ML Engineer

mithleshupadhyay515@gmail.com +91-9311-3040-75 • Chitrakoot, MP

in /in/mithlesh-upadhyay/ () /mithleshupadhyay

Profile

- Data Scientist with 2.7 years of experience.
- Hold M.Tech in Artificial Intelligence from Delhi Govt Engineering College.
- Developed projects utilizing **LLM**, **RAG**, **Embeddings**, **Python**, **Pandas**, Matplotlib, and NLP techniques.
- Successfully fine-tuned open source models like LlaMA 2 and PoC for RAG for AI chatbot building.
- Managed teams for data science and AI content and course preparation.
- Currently looking out for **Data Scientist | Generative AI/ML Engineer** roles.

Skills

Machine Learning & Deep Learning

TensorFlow, PyTorch, LLMs, RLHF, GPT, QLoRA, Model Deployment (SageMaker, Docker)

Data Engineering & Pipelines

Python, Pandas, ETL, Data Cleaning

Cloud Technology

AWS (SageMaker, EC2, S3), Docker, Kubernetes, GitHub

Vector Databases

Chroma DB, FAISS, Pinecone

Natural Language Processing (NLP)

NLTK, Spacy, BERT, BART, Prompt Engineering

Data Visualization & EDA

Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly

Frameworks

LangChain, LlamaIndex, FastAPI, Flask, Streamlit

Vector Databases

SQL, MySQL, MongoDB

Professional Experience

SDE-I (AI Engineer), Propellyr.com

• **Fine-tuned** open source models like **LlaMA 2 using QLoRA** on proprietary datasets and conducted inference.

• Implemented RAG for AI chatbot building and conducted **proof of concept (POC)** for various AI initiatives.

- Extracted data from the Propellyr website and applied **embedding with Faiss DB** to build an interactive chatbot.
- Prepared a dataset to fine-tune Llama 2 for a flight ticket booking chatbot.
- Developed scalable APIs.
- Huggingface profile https://huggingface.co/mithlesh ☑

Software Developer, *ValueMatrix.ai*

- Solved bugs and created new functionalities using JavaScript, Reactjs, MongoDB, HTML, and CSS.
- Participated in meetings and collaborated within teams.

11/2023 - 08/2024

Delhi, India

04/2023 - 09/2023

Bengaluru, India

 ValueMatrix is an AI-powered hiring platform where I resolved bugs using ReactJS.

Python Developer, FORESIET

• Developed functions for APK crawlers.

• Foresiet is a leading cybersecurity company where I worked as a **Python** developer.

09/2022 - 12/2022

Bengaluru, India

09/2017 - 12/2021

Noida, India

Senior Technical Content Engineer, *GeeksforGeeks*

• Managed teams for data science and AI content and course preparation.

• Published articles, provided feedback, and managed content.

- **Published more than 7000 articles**, 3000 improvements, 9000 provided feedback.
- Managed team of 15+ members to deliver products before the deadlines.
- Mentored and guided new members.

Education

M.Tech, Artificial Intelligence, Delhi Technological University (Formerly DCE)

• Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, NLP, Artificial Neural Network, Deep Learning, Computer Vision

07/2021 - 06/2023

Delhi, India

Bachelor of Engineering (CSE), Vindhya Institute of Technology & Science

Algorithms and Data Structure, DBMS, OS, CN

09/2008 – 05/2012

Satna, MP, India

Projects

Flight Agent Chatbot using RAG - LangChain

- Developed a chatbot for flight-related queries using the RAG (Retrieval-Augmented Generation) model.
- Used OpenAI Embeddings and Chroma as vectorstore, and gpt-3.5-turbo for chatbot.
- The chatbot, integrated with **LangChain**, provides users with **real-time assistance** and information regarding flights and related services.

Sales Manufacturing Prediction

- Analyzed and **compared the performance** of various **regression models** for predicting sales in manufacturing.
- Explored different regression techniques to find the most accurate model for sales forecasting.
- Applied **feature engineering techniques** to improve model performance.

mithlesh/LlaMA-2-ayurveda

- Uploaded to the Hugging Face Model Hub.
- This project involves an ayurveda-specific adaptation of the LlaMA 2 language model.
- Users can access and utilize the model for tasks related to ayurvedic **text processing and generation**.

Fine_Tune_LlaMA_2_using_QLoRA

- Fine-tuned the LlaMA 2 model on proprietary datasets.
- Conducted inference using the fine-tuned model.
- Fine-tuned Llama 2 using different datasets on Amazon SageMaker.
- Developed a dataset for flight ticket booking information in JSON format.

Publications

A Comprehensive Analysis of Sentiment Analysis: Approaches, Applications, and Classifier Comparisons, /EEE \square

16/12/2023

- Reviewed popular methods for **sentiment analysis** and how they are used in different applications.
- Analyzed how **text data** from social media and messaging apps can provide valuable feedback.
- Created a guide for **choosing the right** sentiment analysis models based on specific needs.
- IEEE Xplore DOI: 10.1109/ICAC3N60023.2023.10541746 ♂

Courses

GATE CS Score Card, *GATE Authority*

• Qualified GATE CS with good AIR multiple times, (AIR - 2226 in year 2022 out of 1 lac aspirants)

Generative AI with Large Language Models, Coursera

• Foundational knowledge, practical skills, and a functional understanding of how generative AI works

Learn LangChain: Build #22 LLM Apps using OpenAI & Llama 2, *Udemy*

• Build Real World LLM powered applications with LangChain, OpenAI, Llama2, Hugging Face.